

Tamás Nagy Assistant Professor

January 2024

Institute of Psychololgy, Eötvös Loránd University

+36 30 627 6313

nagytamas.netlify.app

nagytamas.hungary@gmail.com

y nagyt

nthun

tamas-nagy-phd-549bbb42

About me -

Tamás Nagy is an assistant professor of psychology at Eötvös Loránd University, Budapest. He has been teaching advanced research methodology, data analysis and statistical inference, and R programming for psychology students. He leads the ELTE Stress and Emotions Lab, which uses experimental methods and psychophysiology to uncover how we perceive physiological arousal, and how it affects our emotions, cognition, and behavior.

Research interests

- The psychophysiology of human stress and emotions
- Machine learning, artificial intelligence, and computational science
- · Improving psychological science

Academic and industry positions

2017- Assistant professor

Eötvös Loránd University, Institute of Psych.

Budapest, Hungary

- Main activities: Teaching, research, supervising graduate and undergraduate students, leading Ph.D. projects, overseeing the faculty's talent management program, managing grants, leading the Stress & Emotions Lab
- Main achievements: reforming the 'Data Analysis and Statistical Inference' course for psychology undergraduates, establishing the R programming training for graduate students, creating a free online course for high school students called 'The Science of Psychology', winning and managing two research grants and four talent management grants, successfully increasing the number of students in the talent management program, open science

2014-2017 Lead researcher

Synetiq Ltd.

Budapest, Hungary

- Main activities: Designing, managing, and analyzing neuromarkerting research projects at a startup company
- Main achievements: Creating the research protocol involving psychophysiological methods and surveys. Leading successful research projects for large media and retail companies including HBO, AXN, RTL, BBC, The Dutch National TV, Lidl, Tesco, etc. Managed a research team to conduct media studies.

2012-2013 Research trainee

The University of Amsterdam

Amsterdam, The Netherlands

 Main activities: Writing a manuscript on the effect of the acute stress response on alpha-amylase and cardiovascular indicators. PI: Dr. Jos Bosch

2008-2010 Research assistant

Hungarian Academy of Sciences

Budapest, Hungary

 Main activities: Analyzing and planning of quantitative studies, preparing manuscripts in the Comparative Cross-cultural Psychology Lab

2006-2008 Counseling psychologist

Budapest University of Tech. and Econ.

Budapest, Hungary

Budapest, Hungary

Main activities: Psychological counseling for students, conducting psychological measurements

Education

2019-2023	Postdoctoral fellow Budapest, Hungary	Eötvös Loránd University
2010-2015	Ph.D. studies in Psychology Budapest, Hungary	Eötvös Loránd University
2001-2006	M.A. studies in Psychology	Eötvös Loránd University

University offices and memberships

2023- Member of the Institutional Research Ethics Board.
 2022- Head of the Stress & Emotions Research Group.
 2019-2021 Acting head of the Social Interventions Research Group.
 2019- Member of the Research Transparency Committee.
 2018- Member of the ELTE Talent Management Council.
 2018- Faculty head of the Scientific Student Circle of ELTE PPK.

Grants

2018-2022 National Talent Program

Amount: HUF 10.4M

 Description: Short (1 year) grants to fund the faculty talent management program

2019-2023 Postdoctoral grant

• Amount: HUF 25.5M

 Description: National Scientific Basic Research Programs - Research grant to study the role of emotional arousal in media-induced stress recovery

2018-2021 Young researcher grant

Amount: HUF 28.5M

 Description: National Scientific Basic Research Programs - Research grant to study the effects of intelligence mindset and mindfulness meditation on performance

Awards and honors

2021 ELTE Online course development award

 For creating e-learning material for 'Data analysis and Statistical Inference' course.

2020 ELTE's Promising Researcher Special Award for Open Science

• For outstanding achievements in the field of open

science

2018 Erasmus+ research and training mobility

Participation in a Bayesian statistics workshop in

Amsterdam

2016 Special prize at the Brain and Vision Hackathon

 For integrating EEG systems into mobile, PC, and web applications

2012-2013 Erasmus+ traineeship

· University of Amsterdam, Netherlands

2010-2014 Hungarian state scholarship

To pursue doctoral studies at ELTE

Teaching experience

- Data analysis and statistical inference lecture (B.A., Hungarian)
- Multivariate statistics lecture (M.A., Hungarian and English)
- Statistical programming and data analysis in R seminar M.A. and Ph.D, English)
- Advanced research methodology in clinical and health psychology seminar (M.A., English)
- Advanced data analysis methods in R seminar (M.A., Hungarian and English)

orkshops held

2022	 Regression Summer School 22 Regression summer course jointly held students of ELTE and University of https://osf.io/em5k4/ 	
2022	Vienna Power Analyis in R WorkshopWorkshop about simulation based power a in R, https://osf.io/2tp3y/	University of Vienna analysis

2022 Introduction to R and the Tidyverse University of Vienna
• Two day introduction to R, https://osf.io/mx3vw/

Model of the decision to K, https://osino/mxsvw/

Meta-analysis Workshop Semmelweiss University
• Workshop about the theory and practice of meta-

analysis (Hungarian), https://osf.io/ug8cz/

Open Science Workshop Eötvös Loránd University

Workshop about open science practices (Hungarian), https://osf.io/fz3pb/

2020 Open Science Workshop

Eötvös Loránd University

Workshop about open science practices (Hungarian), https://osf.io/swntk/

Languages

2022

2021

- English (professional level)
- Hungarian (native language)
- · German (limited professional level)
- · Japanese (basic level)

Programming languages and data science tools

- R: developer level
- · git, markdown: professional level
- SQL, python, Matlab, latex: basic level (I can use them but prefer R and other tools whenever possible)
- SPSS, JASP, JAMOVI: professional level (I can teach these, and tutor others, but I don't use them myself)

Journal positions and activity

- Ad hoc peer review activity at multiple journals: https://www.webofscience.com/wos/author/record/J-5969-2019
- Associate editor at Hungarian Psychology Review (Magyar Pszichológiai Szemle)

Society memberships

- Hungarian Psychological Society
- Society for the Improvement of Psychological Science
- Member of the public body of Hungarian Academy of Sciences
- · Member of the Psychological Science Accelerator

Working papers and manuscripts under review

Hajdú, N., Szászi, B., Aczél, B., & Nagy, T. (Under review). Using supervised machine learning methods in psychological research. *Magyar Pszichológiai Szemle*.

Nagy, T., Hergert, J., Rubínová, E., Tyson, G., Wallrich, L., Elsherif, M., Skvortsova, A., Payne, J., Alarie, S., Wang, Y. A., Graves, K., Schmidt, K., Sotola, L., Waltzer, T., Gjoneska, B., Seetahul, Y., Yang, Y.-F., Scharfenberg, D., & Moreau, D. (Under review). The Questionable Research Practice Bestiary. *Advances in Methods and Practices in Psychological Science*.

Nagy, T., Ipacs, H., Ferentzi, E., & Köteles, F. (Under review). Heart rate perception and expectation impact laboratory-induced perceived stress. *Biological Psychology*.

Peer reviewed journal articles and book chapters

- Terry, J., Ross, R. M., Nagy, T., Salgado, M., Garrido-Vásquez, P., Sarfo, J. O., Cooper, S., Buttner, A. C., Lima, T. J. S., Öztürk, İ., Akay, N., Santos, F. H., Artemenko, C., Copping, L. T., Elsherif, M. M., Milovanović, I., Cribbie, R. A., Drushlyak, M. G., Swainston, K., ... Field, A. P. (2023). Data from an international Multi-Centre study of statistics and mathematics anxieties and related variables in university students (the SMARVUS dataset). Journal of Open Psychology Data, 11(1), 8. https://doi.org/10.5334/jopd.80
- Nagy, T., Sik, K., Török, L., Beáta Bőthe, Takacs, Z. K., & Orosz, G. (2023). Brief growth mindset and mindfulness inductions to facilitate task persistence after negative feedback. *Collabra. Psychology*, 9(1). https://doi.org/10.1525/collabra.74253
- 3. Hoogeveen, S., Sarafoglou, A., Aczel, B., Aditya, Y., Alayan, A. J., Allen, P. J., Altay, S., Alzahawi, S., Amir, Y., Anthony, F.-V., Kwame Appiah, O., Atkinson, Q. D., Baimel, A., Balkaya-Ince, M., Balsamo, M., Banker, S., Bartoš, F., Becerra, M., Beffara, B., ... Wagenmakers, E.-J. (2022). A manyanalysts approach to the relation between religiosity and well-being. *Religion, Brain & Behavior*, 1–47. https://doi.org/10.1080/2153599X. 2022.2070255
- 4. Salamon, J., Blume, B. D., Tóth-Király, I., Nagy, T., & Orosz, G. (2022). The positive gain spiral of job resources, work engagement, opportunity and motivation on training transfer. *International Journal of Training and Development*, 26(3), 556–580. https://doi.org/10.1111/ijtd.12277
- Bago, B., Kovacs, M., Protzko, J., Nagy, T., Kekecs, Z., Palfi, B., Adamkovic, M., Adamus, S., Albalooshi, S., Albayrak-Aydemir, N., Alfian, I. N., Alper, S., Alvarez-Solas, S., Alves, S. G., Amaya, S., Andresen, P. K., Anjum, G., Ansari, D., Arriaga, P., ... Aczel, B. (2022). Situational factors shape moral judgements in the trolley dilemma in eastern, southern and western countries in a culturally diverse sample. Nature Human Behaviour, 6(6), 880–895. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-022-01319-5
- 6. Maraz, A., Nagy, T., & Ziegler, M. (2022). Negativity in delayed affective recall is related to the borderline personality trait. *Scientific Reports*, 12(1), 3505. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-022-07358-2
- Coles, N. A., March, D. S., Marmolejo-Ramos, F., Larsen, J. T., Arinze, N. C., Ndukaihe, I. L. G., Willis, M. L., Foroni, F., Reggev, N., Mokady, A., Forscher, P. S., Hunter, J. F., Kaminski, G., Yüvrük, E., Kapucu, A., Nagy, T., Hajdu, N., Tejada, J., Freitag, R. M. K., ... Liuzza, M. T. (2022). A multi-lab test of the facial feedback hypothesis by the many smiles collaboration. Nature Human Behaviour, 6(12), 1731–1742. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-022-01458-9
- 8. Salamon, J., Blume, B. D., Orosz, G., & Nagy, T. (2022). The moderating effect of coworkers' training participation on the influence of peer support in the transfer process. *European Journal of Training and Development*, 47(10), 15–36. https://doi.org/10.1108/EJTD-07-2021-0102
- 9. Salamon, J., Tóth-Király, I., Bõthe, B., Nagy, T., & Orosz, G. (2021). Having the cake and eating it too: First-Order, Second-Order and bifactor representations of work engagement. *Frontiers in Psychology*, *12*, 615581. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2021.615581
- Maraz, A., Nagy, T., & Ziegler, M. (2021). When bad gets worse: Negative wording amplifies negative recall in persons with the borderline personality trait. *Applied Cognitive Psychology*, 35(1), 274–285. https://doi.org/10.1002/acp.3764
- 11. Salamon, J., Blume, B. D., Orosz, G., & Nagy, T. (2021). The interplay between the level of voluntary participation and supervisor support on trainee motivation and transfer. *Human Resource Development Quarterly*, 32(4), 459–481. https://doi.org/10.1002/hrdq.21428
- Simor, P., Polner, B., Báthori, N., Sifuentes-Ortega, R., Van Roy, A., Albajara Sáenz, A., Luque González, A., Benkirane, O., Nagy, T., & Peigneux, P. (2021). Home confinement during the COVID-19: Day-to-day associations of sleep quality with rumination, psychotic-like experiences, and somatic symptoms. Sleep, 44(7). https://doi.org/10.1093/sleep/zsab029
- Zavecz, Z., Nagy, T., Galkó, A., Nemeth, D., & Janacsek, K. (2020). The relationship between subjective sleep quality and cognitive performance in healthy young adults: Evidence from three empirical studies. *Scientific Reports*, 10(1), 4855. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-61627-6

- 14. Ferentzi, E., & Nagy, T. (2019). Emotions and heartbeat perception. In F. Köteles & E. Ferentzi (Eds.), *Tanulmányok az interocepcióról. Bárdos györgy professzor tiszteletére* (pp. 201–221). ELTE Eötvös Kiadó. https://m2.mtmt.hu/api/publication/31034038
- Simor, P., Steinbach, E., Nagy, T., Gilson, M., Farthouat, J., Schmitz, R., Gombos, F., Ujma, P. P., Pamula, M., Bódizs, R., & Peigneux, P. (2018). Lateralized rhythmic acoustic stimulation during daytime NREM sleep enhances slow waves. Sleep, 41(12). https://doi.org/10.1093/sleep/zsy176
- 16. Nagy, T. (2016). *Psychophysiological responses to distress and eustress* (M. Fülöp & G. Bárdos, Eds.) [PhD thesis, ELTE Eötvös Loránd University]. https://doi.org/10.13140/RG.2.1.5154.3207
- 17. Fülöp, M., & Nagy, T. (2015). Coping with winning and losing: Comparing adolescents and young people on the verge of adulthood. *Magyar Pszichológiai Szemle*, 70(1), 95–119. https://doi.org/10.1556/0016. 2015.70.1.7
- Nagy, T., Kovács, K. J., Polyák, Á., Harmat, L., Bárdos, G., & Fülöp, M. (2015). The effect of competitive reward on salivary testosterone levels and performance in young adult men: The role of hypercompetition. Magyar Pszichológiai Szemle, 70(1), 121–141. https://doi.org/10.1556/0016.2015.70.1.8
- Nagy, T., Salavecz, G., Simor, P., Purebl, G., Bódizs, R., Dockray, S., & Steptoe, A. (2015). Frequent nightmares are associated with blunted cortisol awakening response in women. *Physiology & Behavior*, 147, 233–237. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.physbeh.2015.05.001
- 20. Nagy, T., Lien, R. van, Willemsen, G., Proctor, G., Efting, M., Fülöp, M., Bárdos, G., Veerman, E. C. I., & Bosch, J. A. (2015). A fluid response: Alpha-amylase reactions to acute laboratory stress are related to sample timing and saliva flow rate. *Biological Psychology*, 109, 111–119. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biopsycho.2015.04.012
- 21. Nagy, T., Tellez, D., Divák, Á., Lógó, E., Köles, M., & Hámornik, B. (2014). Predicting arousal with machine learning of EEG signals. *2014 5th IEEE Conference on Cognitive Infocommunications (CogInfoCom)*, 137–140. https://doi.org/10.1109/CogInfoCom.2014.7020434
- 22. Bálint, K., Nagy, T., & Csabai, M. (2014). The effect of patient-centeredness and gender of professional role models on trainees' mentalization responses. Implications for film-aided education. *Patient Education and Counseling*, 97(1), 52–58. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pec. 2014.06.005
- 23. Kekecs, Z., Nagy, T., & Varga, K. (2014). The effectiveness of suggestive techniques in reducing postoperative side effects: A meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. *Anesthesia and Analgesia*, 119(6), 1407–1419. https://doi.org/10.1213/ANE.0000000000000466